Hello everyone, welcome back to Nagarjuna.
This is the tenth lesson of the venerated Nagarjuna.
We will be discussing
BCINGS PA DANG THAR PA BRTAG PA
BCINGS PA DANG THAR PA BRTAG PA.
Repeat after us: BCINGS PA, DANG
THAR PA, BRTAG PA.
What is BRTAG PA?
In Sanskrit, it
is
PARĪKṢĀ (PARIKSHA).
Regarding BCINGS PA and THAR PA:
BCINGS PA means bondage,
like being chained in a prison.
THAR PA means freedom.
Now we will discuss the
emptiness of being bound in samsara,
and the emptiness of being free from those bondages. Let's
look at the first sentence, which is
actually only half a sentence. It
begins with GAL TE. A
fellow man... Nagarjuna,
is asking another person:
"Who is in samsara?"
Who is in this cycle of samsara?
Who is going around in circles in samsara?
This is an interesting question.
Incidentally, if you don't understand
who is going around in samsara,
you will be going around in samsara yourself.
So it's a pretty good question.
GAL TE
'DU BYED 'KHOR ZHE NA,
DE DAG RTAG NA MI 'KHOR TE,
GAL TE means that
Nagarjuna was talking to another person: "
Who is wandering in samsara?" The
other person said: 'DU BYED'.
This is a confusing answer
because 'DU BYED' means cause and effect.
In fact, it is also
the name of the second stage of the wheel of life, that is,
karma.
But that is completely unrelated to the meaning
here. Here it refers to PHUNG PO,
body and mind.
Lately I like to call it body and mind because it is easier to understand. It is exactly what we call body and mind.
If you say that what is going around in samsara
is the combination of body and mind, both body and mind together
'KHOR ZHE NA',
then do you think of body and mind
as unchanging or changing?
When you're asked, "Who travels through samsara? Who is reborn again and again?" and you answer "body and mind," specifically
Michael's body and mind, I say, "Is it something unchanging,
or something that changes?"
Nagarjuna usually gives both answers. The other person says it's unchanging, something that remains constant. Oh, if Michael's body and mind are unchanging, by the way, that leads to eternity, doesn't it?
Some people mistranslate this word.
It leads to eternity. If Michael's eternal body and mind are constantly traveling in the cycle of reincarnation, then it cannot go in circles. Why? Because it is RTAG PA, because it is unchanging, to go around in circles you must change. Through going around in circles you will change. Going around in circles means you will change. If you don't change, you can't go to other places. At least you have to change where you sit.
Some things have to change when you travel. Therefore, it can't be
Michael. Michael's unchanging body and mind
because it has to be reborn again and again. Then
another person will come back and say: "Okay, then I'll
change my story. It's a body and
mind that change." Here is the
next sentence.
Yay~ By the way, the second half of
this verse has been split up again. The first part of the second half is MI RTAG NA YANG 'KHOR MI 'GYUR
MI RTAG NA YANG 'KHOR MI 'GYUR If you say that Michael's body and mind change, then they can't go around in the cycle of rebirth. Why?
Because they disappear every thousandth of a second, understand?
They can maintain... SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS ... The definition of change SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS Repeat SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS This could be a good song SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS... It means things that appear and
disappear SKAD CIG every moment SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS How can it go on forever? If it disappears every thousandth of a second, how can something that
disappears every thousandth of a second go around in circles? It's impossible. Why? Because
every thousandth of a second of Michael's mind and body is separate from the previous thousandth of a second of Michael's mind and body, right? We have spent a long time explaining SAṂSARGA (SANSARGA) Christina,
SANSARGA
flows together. Yes,
if Geshe-la's mind and body are like tap, tap, tap, tap, then
each moment is separate. Then there is
no reason
why this should go to that, because they never touch. So this can also become Tim's mind and body,
right? Since they are not connected anyway, if Michael
's mind and body are like this, why can't Michael's mind and body be like this and then become Tim in the
next moment? Why not?
There's no reason
why I can't
become Tim. Tim and Geshe-sensei aren't connected either. If there's no connection between Geshe-sensei and Geshe-sensei, but Geshe-sensei can move from one moment to the next like this, then Geshe-sensei's body and mind can also become Tim's body and mind. Then I can go there and join Tim's cycle of reincarnation,
right? Do
you understand? If they are separate, anything can happen,
but it
cannot be connected. It cannot be a continuous stream. Why? Because it will remain unchanged, then you will
not have different births,
and you will always be stuck in the same moment, just like... what is the name of that movie? "Temporarily suspended today." Yes, "Temporarily suspended today." Okay, next sentence.
Where? We should have a picture,
right? Let's talk about circles. I think it should be seconds. Lama Qiuni said:
If Geshe's mind and body can only last for
one-thousandth of a second,
how can he have time to circle?
You can't form a
circle with just one point. You can't draw a circle with just one point.
Okay, next sentence: SEMS CAN LA YANG RIM 'DI MTSUNGS SEMS CAN LA YANG RIM 'DI MTSUNGS SEMS CAN means living beings. You can also say sentient beings. I don't like this word because it's not really English. You wouldn't usually say it like that
in English.
How is your sentient being mother? Anyway, it refers to biological
SEMS CAN LA YANG, RIM RIM. What does it mean? Like Lam Rim (steps),
in Nagarjuna Rim,
Rim has a special meaning. It means the steps leading to the argument I just gave you. Those steps that lead to the final argument are called Rim (steps) in Nagarjuna's words. When you see Nagarjuna mention Rim,
you should think: the steps leading to my final argument.
What does that mean here? If you say that what is circling in
the wheel of life is not Geshe-la's mind and body, but Geshe-la himself, then that is RIM MTSUNGS, the same
argument, returning to the same argument, what is that? What was the
first question Nagarjuna asked? Don't forget we've already discussed body and mind. Now that person says, "Okay, body and mind can't go in circles, so it must be Geshe-la-shi who's going in circles." Alright, let's do the same argument. We
asked him two questions: If
you say Geshe-la-shi is going in circles in samsara,
then is the Geshe-la-shi you're talking about unchanging? He started by talking about what is unchanging, but I don't
know why you're talking about the unchanging Geshe teacher?
Yes, yes, I'm talking about the unchanging
Geshe teacher. How could he possibly go in circles? Because he's always at the same point. He's the same person. He won't become an animal, a celestial being, or a being from hell. He will always be the
Geshe teacher. He can't
change. So what is the second RIM PA? Or are
you saying that Geshe-la (Geshe teacher) is subject to change? So he is the various random moments of
Geshe-la-shi. In that case, we have already proved with the contact argument that there is not
necessarily a connection between Geshe-la-shi's first
moment and Geshe-la-shi's second moment. Geshe-la-shi's first
moment can become Tim's second moment. So who is going around in circles? Therefore, no one is in the cycle of reincarnation, no one travels through the wheel of life. Why? Because it is neither Geshe-la-shi's mind and body nor
Geshe-la-shi, why? Because it's neither a Geshe teacher with a body and mind that can change and remain unchanged, nor a Geshe teacher with a body and mind that
can change and remain unchanged, then there's nothing else.
No one is
going around in circles in the cycle of reincarnation.
Okay, we have a picture. By the way, there's a concept that Lama Chuni likes to talk about... He said, don't forget,
when we mention Geshe teachers,
relative to the body and mind of a
Geshe teacher, we're talking about something like a soul
. Is there a huge Geshe teacher who keeps
reincarnating again and again? He doesn't look like a Geshe teacher; it's unrelated to body and mind.
There's some kind of inner soul or essence of a Geshe teacher who acquires different bodies and minds, right? He will
discard the old body and mind
and acquire a new body and mind.
Therefore, there is a Geshe teacher who is unrelated to the Geshe teacher's body and mind. The
Geshe teacher has this third part, which is the
"super inner Geshe teacher".
And the inner Geshe teacher will continuously change his body and mind.
This is the second argument, which
I will talk about.
In fact, that is what the whole chapter is about. Don't cheat yet, let's continue. That is
actually the focus of the whole chapter.
Good question.
Let's continue.
The next sentence is
GAL TE GANG ZAG 'KHOR ZHE NA,
PHUNG PO SKYE MCHED KHAMS RNAMS LA,
DE NI RNAM PA LNGAS BTZAL NA,
MED NA GANG ZHIG 'KHOR BAR 'GYUR.
This part has two sentences, and this is the first sentence. GAL TE GANG ZAG
'KHOR ZHE NA.
That person insists,
no, that is the Geshe teacher.
That GANG ZAG, PURUSHA
is the Geshe teacher from one life to the next.
He discards the old body and mind and acquires a new body and mind. Just like
some high school boys treat their girlfriends,
or some high school girls treat their boyfriends, he abandons one body and mind and takes another, and then changes to yet
another,
but he continues to attend high school.
That person said that it is indeed Geshe-laoshi constantly being reborn.
So let's examine the
relationship between Geshe-laoshi and his body and mind.
If it is indeed Geshe-laoshi constantly
abandoning his body and mind
and taking on a new one, then what is the relationship between Geshe-laoshi and his body and mind
?
Because of certain relationships between him and his body and mind,
he cannot
change his body and mind. If Geshe-la is his body and mind, then he cannot abandon his body and mind to be
reborn into the next life
because he will disappear.
If Geshe-la is his body and mind,
once he abandons his body and mind to obtain the next body and mind, Geshe-la is
no longer the same body and mind as before.
He must be some kind of
superhuman who can change his body and mind, right?
So what exactly is their relationship?
Nagarjuna said: Okay, okay.
Geshe-sensei will continue, right? Is it possible for Geshe teachers to have their bodies and minds replaced? So, it couldn't be
Geshe-laoshi's mind and body, right?
Why?
Because he will abandon his body and mind and go somewhere else. If he only has his body and mind and he abandons his body and mind, then
he will disappear. Do you
understand?
There is no Geshe teacher who can change body and mind,
because he is his body and mind.
We should look at the
relationship between the Geshe teacher and his body and mind.
Then he said RNAM
PA LNGAS BCOL. All the texts have RNAM PA LNGAS BCOL, which is
completely misspelled.
I should correct it.
Tim, if you can imagine that
the letters CA - ཅ in the first column,
with naro on top, is CO - ཅོ, right?
But if you draw a naro with a
single horn—by the way, naro means horn—
what would it become? The
CA with a small flag next to it
becomes TZA - ཙ, right?
All the texts write BCOL - བཅོལ,
they're all wrong, it should be BTZAL - བཙལ.
This is the first problem.
You might spend two days
looking up the word BCOLs in the dictionary and
you'll never find it.
And all the engravings are wrong.
This makes someone very unhappy.
DE NI RNAM PA LNGAS BTZAL NA. If
you...
BTZAL means something like PHYAG 'TSAL. What is 'TSAL
' in PHYAG 'TSAL? But what does it really mean? Seeking grace
from the Guru. BTZAL means seeking, searching. So here it means searching. There are five different ways of
RNAM PA LNGA. There are five possible relationships between
Michael and his body and mind. Let's look at these five relationships. If you say that Michael is constantly being reborn, constantly changing his body and mind, then let's look at what possible relationships exist between Michael and his body and mind. But Nagarjuna won't... tell you which five they are. He
never mentions
which five
they are. He never tells you which five relationships they are. This is where Geshe-laoshi is reading late into
the night: My God, where exactly are the five relationships written? If you were a Geshe teacher and encountered this situation late at night
, and you had to teach the next morning, what would you do? You would search for Gofer, search the database. I searched the database and the first answer I got was Rendawa. We call him Jezun Rendawa. Do
you know who Jezun Rendawa is? He was a Sakya master, Tsongkhapa's teacher, one of Tsongkhapa's main teachers. They started as teacher and student, but later collaborated to form a teaching team.
They would teach the Vinaya together, and so on. Incidentally,
Rendawa wrote a very brilliant commentary on the *Letter to a Friend*, concise, sweet, and precise. He also wrote a commentary on
Nagarjuna's *Treatise on Wisdom*, also concise and precise. So I
started by looking there.
After looking at his work for a while, I looked at Tsongkhapa's
commentary on
Nagarjuna's *
Treatise on Wisdom*, called... yes, *The Ocean of Reasoning*. That's the ship we're on. We're trying to cross the sea. So, combining all of them, I got some good answers. That's the beauty of this text. Everyone has tried to interpret it, and it's difficult, really difficult. Therefore, there are
hundreds of commentaries on this text.
Chandrakirti
also tried to interpret it, right? Let's look at the following five possible relationships between Michael and Michael's mind and body. Here are the five relationships between them. What is my final
conclusion? Oh, to be
fair to Nagarjuna, he has already given five relationships in the text, but we have forgotten that he gave them a long time ago. At that time, he
was talking about the relationship between certain things and certain things. What was it again? He had already discussed the
relationship between fire and firewood back then, which is why he wasn't lazy
.
He had already mentioned the five possible relationships when he talked about the relationship between fire
and firewood. So he probably sat there impatiently and said, "Idiot, stop asking me! Go back to Chapter 10, sentence 14!" I
checked and it said, "I already
mentioned it back then, so don't say I didn't tell you which
five relationships. I expected you to remember." These are the following five. You might have quickly skimmed through them and then stopped thinking about them, but let's think about it carefully. Let's start with Tim. Is Tim his mind and body? In this discussion, let's not forget that the topic is how Tim is reborn life after life in the cycle of existence. The
question is quite simple: Is Tim... Is Tim's current body and mind all that he is? No, because if it dies, Tim disappears and
no one continues the cycle of reincarnation. Therefore, Tim cannot be equal to Tim's body and mind because someone must acquire the body and mind, and someone must abandon that body and mind. Now,
continuing with Patch, the second question is whether
Patch is completely separated from his body and mind. Look, his body and mind just collapsed immediately. No, they must have some connection. They must have some connection, right?
Otherwise, you would be Tim. Otherwise, Patch would become Tim. He would grab the mind and body closest to him.
Therefore, there must be a Patch who is not separate from his mind and body. There must be a Patch who is connected to his mind and body in some way. You can
say that there is a
Patch who is separate from his mind and body, but he must also be entangled with his mind and body to some extent.
Otherwise, he would be entangled with Rebecca's mind and body. Then you would have difficulty even combing your hair, and you would have a beard, etc. All sorts of philosophical problems would arise.
Okay, so Tim is not his mind and body,
but Patch is not completely separate from
his mind and body. There is a certain
degree of connection. Okay, the third possibility: Does Rebecca's mind and body contain Rebecca to
some extent? If we look at it from the opposite perspective, then we are no longer looking at whether Rebecca has a mind and body, but rather whether that other mind and
body reached out and grabbed
Rebecca. This idea is strange, but it's the third of five possibilities. To some extent, it's your mind and body that drew you
in. It's the gravity of your
mind and body that pulled Rebecca in. So Rebecca got stuck in Rebecca's mind and body. That's the third possibility. It's a bit silly, but not entirely. The fourth possibility, is Pao ready? Pao doesn't depend on her body and mind. You can do anything to her body and mind without affecting Pao. You can get infected with
the virus, you can get vaccinated, but Pao doesn't care. Pao is an individual separate from her body and mind. Pao is not situated above
her body and mind.
This is the fourth possibility, right? We have four, right? 1, 2, 3, 4
Christina, are you ready? Christina's
mind and body do not depend
on Christina, so Christina can run away. But Christina's mind and body are still typing in the chair. That is the fifth possibility. And all five possibilities are a bit untenable. They are all a bit unlikely. They sound impossible. What do you think of when you think about traveling in the
cycle of reincarnation? What do you think is the relationship between you and your mind and body? Can you abandon your body and mind, yet still have something left to continue and exchange for a new body and mind? Can you exist without a
body and mind? Can my body and mind exist without you? Can it
continue without you?
When you're contemplating the cycle of life and reincarnation, you haven't truly grasped the concept. This is what Nagarjuna is trying to say. Perhaps
you have some understanding of it, but I
think most people feel... at least I grew up in a Christian culture, a Judeo-Christian culture. I feel that some Michael's soul
acquired a body and mind
and held it for a while, then they separated, and the soul continued. Then the soul
had to find a new body and mind, or something like that. In this way, you can do anything to the
body and mind;
you can abuse them, but the soul transcends all of that. The soul has no effect whatsoever, and so on.
Judeo-Christian culture has its objections to this issue because we grew up in that culture, so we have this feeling. But if you really examine it, is it justifiable? Is this reasonable? Are you completely independent of your
mind and body? Is there a Rebecca who is completely unaffected by physical
and mental factors? If you're interested,
you can go back and look at sentence 14 of chapter 10. They're discussing whether firewood is fire. That's the same argument, which is why Nagarjuna doesn't repeat it. GAL TE MANG POS BKUR BA. Sorry, no, that's all.
Okay, let's go to... 'DU BYED. Didn't we talk about the third sentence, NYE BAR LEN? Oh,
you're right, Part Two. Oh yes, this is tricky. I don't know why I skipped it. Let's
go back. We know what
you're talking about. NYE BAR LEN NAS NYER LEN PAR, 'KHOR NA SRID PA MED PAR 'GYUR, SRID MED NYE BAR LEN MED NA, DE GANG CI ZHIG 'KHOR BAR 'GYUR, This is tricky
because
NYE BAR LEN PA is a very difficult term in Buddhist philosophy. It means to closely bear NYE BAR LEN PA, but here it means to acquire a new body and mind at the time of rebirth. Even if this term implies something
?
Yes, someone obtained it. So, according to ancient Buddhism, rebirth is called embracing another, meaning another body and mind. Therefore, Nagarjuna used it in the word rebirth. He used this word to represent rebirth. He said, "Is rebirth...?" What happens between each rebirth? Let's look at it, and then
we can decide what the relationship is between you and your body and mind. Let's see how you go from one
rebirth to the next. Then we can decide what the relationship is between Tim and
Tim's body and mind. Here he says NYE ​​BAR LEN NAS NYER LEN PAR. For
example, when you change from
one identity to another, and then the
Khuni Lama says... I don't understand why he says that. "If you are reborn from a human to a celestial being," reborn into a sacred and temporary suffering being, this is somewhat implying that we are doing meditation 'KHOR NA SRID PA MED PAR 'GYUR,' then there is no SRID PA in 'KHOR BA.' KHOR BA is samsara.
SRID PA here means... Here you need the Khuni Lama again. It doesn't refer to SRID PA, which originally means samsara, like SRID PA'I 'KHOR LO BHAVACAKRA, the wheel of life. Here it doesn't mean that.
Here it means BAR SRID. Since you have read the Abhidharma, you will know what BAR SRID BAR DO
SRID PA is. Yes, the beings in the intermediate state (bardo) are called Bar Srid, not the kind of people who work in bars. Bar Srid Khor Na Srid PA Med Par 'Gyur. If
you abandon...
how should I put it?
If you abandon one body and mind, and then in the
next moment acquire another body and mind, then there is no intermediate state.
That's what he was trying to say.
Nagarjuna said, "How do
you go from one rebirth to the next?" Another person said, "Oh, you just abandon one body and mind, and then in a fraction of a second you acquire a new one." Okay, then there is
no
intermediate state. That violates
Buddhist teachings. There should be an intermediate state. It should exist; most rebirths have one. Then that person said, no, no, no.
If there is an interruption between each rebirth, how
can you say there is a cycle of rebirth? If it is interrupted,
how can you say there is a continuous cycle of rebirth? If you say no, no, no, there is an intermediate state (bardo), then there might not be a connection between
abandoning this body and mind
and acquiring your next body and mind, because there's a gap between the two. If there's a gap, it's not a cycle; a cycle can't be
formed. A cycle should be like this: If there's an intermediate state, there's
no reincarnation. If you abandon your body and mind, and there's a gap before you acquire a new body and mind, then there can't be a cycle. It's just a bunch of fragmented pieces
, not a cycle. It doesn't meet the definition of a
cycle. A cycle should be like this: the same thing repeats itself, like technical equipment malfunctioning—it keeps happening. Sorry, I'm not
saying this is real, just saying. By the way, I'm very grateful to the technical team. May God bless them. Now that we've finished the second sentence, let's move on to the next one. Yes, this is a very interesting
continuation. Sometimes Nagarjuna will move on to the next topic, indicating that he thinks he's closed the case, but we (stunned)... He'll
say, "You understand? You understand, it means no one
acquires any body or mind,
and the body and mind have
n't been used by anyone. Okay, let's move on to the next one." And you say, "Eh, wait a minute..." Then we move on to the next sentence. He is about to
delve into another major topic: 'DU BYED MYA NGAN 'DA' BAR NI, JI LTA BUR YANG MI 'THAD DO, SEMS CAN MYA NGAN 'DA' BAR YANG, JI LTA BUR YANG 'THAD MI 'GYUR,'
We will no longer discuss who attained body and mind. Instead, we will discuss who achieved Nirvana and who broke through this cycle. What happened after that? What happens after you break out of the cycle?
We've discussed cycles, but I don't understand.
You can neither attain body and mind nor not attain body and mind. Something's not right. Enough, let's move on to something else. Who attained enlightenment? Who attained Nirvana? What does 'DU BYED MYA NGAN 'DA' BAR NI 'DU BYED' mean in this chapter? The $100 question: What is its significance in this chapter? Cancel the bet... PHUNG PO—
Body
and Mind.
The word "karma" in this chapter refers to your body and mind, that is, things that change. The changing part of Rebecca, as the soul, is stainless steel, an unchanging egg shape, while Rebecca's body and mind,
he calls it the changing part of Rebecca, that is, the thing you acquire and
discard in every lifetime. So he says, does Rebecca's body and mind go to Nirvana? Which part of Rebecca went to Nirvana? Is it Rebecca's mind and body? JI LTA BUR YANG MI 'THAD DO This is the frustrating part of reading Nagarjuna. He
said
no, not Rebecca's mind and body went to Nirvana. Why? Because it exists in itself, please, not her body and mind, because the body and mind will disappear or something like that. Why? Because it exists in itself. It doesn't depend on anything else. It doesn't depend on the seeds of consciousness. It comes from itself and never
disappears. It illogically comes from itself and
illogically maintains its origin from itself. Nothing illogical can make it
disappear. It's an illogical,
unchanging, metallic egg shape
called Rebecca. So, forget it. Nagarjuna is a bit frustrating, like this. This book is a bit frustrating.
Every time he peeks into a corner, he says, "Well, it's impossible anyway." Then you ask why, and
he says it's because you think... You think your husband in the kitchen
comes from himself. You think, "Dude, don't be like that..." If your husband in the kitchen is unhappy because of traffic at work, then your... then your body and mind cannot reach Nirvana.
That's his argument. If your husband comes from himself
, then your body and mind cannot be something that
reaches Nirvana.
Why?
Because the existence of body and mind also comes from itself, it
cannot be
changed
. It cannot reach a sublime state called Nirvana.
Because it
cannot be changed, because it comes from itself. The only way that anything in the universe can be changed is through the seeds of your consciousness. Do
you understand? Then that
person changed their tune. Oh, no, Rebecca's body and mind went to Nirvana. It's... what's the other option?	 It's not Rebecca's body and mind, but Rebecca herself. He calls it GANG ZAG, PARUSHA. Oh no, I've changed my mind. It's
not Rebecca's body and mind that go to Nirvana, but "Rebecca." MYA NGAN 'DA' YANG JI LTA BUR YANG 'THAD MI 'GYUR. Same question, please. Rebecca
comes from herself. She
can't change, she can't go to Nirvana. It's a bit like trying to use what he's trying to prove in his
argument to prove what he's trying to prove. This seems a bit off, but if it really is off, then it proves he's right. Everything is off. Yes, the picture here is a bit fake, but it's just to help
you remember. This is Rebecca's body and mind. It should be mind and body. Which one goes to Nirvana
? I didn't know that Lama Chöni had a particularly convincing—sorry... a particularly convincing—argument here. I'd like to read it.
Sometimes it's good to listen to Lama Chöni
's teachings. We were just listening to Nagarjuna talk about 'DIR 'KHOR MKHAN RANG BZHIN GYIS MED PAR NGES NA'. If 'KHOR MKHAN really is
... then MKHAN is... MKHAN is added to a verb to make it the doer. For example, teacher is SLOB MKHAN.
MKHAN is the -er in English (teach-er). Adding -er after teach makes it the person who teaches. In Tibetan, it's MKHAN. So what is 'KHOR MKHAN'? Yes, the one who goes around in circles in the cycle of rebirth,
'KHOR MKHAN RANG BZHIN GYIS MED PAR NGES NA', as Lama Chöni said, "Why do we talk about this? Why are we so obsessed with this person... obsessed with finding
out who is experiencing reincarnation?" Because if you can find out that he is RANG BZHIN GYIS MED PA, yes, if you can
find out that the person going around in the cycle
of rebirth
does not come from himself, then you can stop going around in the cycle of
rebirth! Do you
understand? This is wonderful. Let me repeat it again. Lama Qiuni said, "Do you want to guess why we are so obsessed with finding out who is cycling through samsara?" We said, "We don't know." He said, "Because we
want to
see that person
actually has no self-nature." Why is that? Because that way you won't have to go through the cycle of reincarnation anymore! It's a very beautiful argument, you know? That's why we've had such a long discussion about
who's going around in the cycle of rebirth. Because by examining the relationship between you and your mind and body, you suddenly realize that you come from yourself, from your seeds, and then you don't have to keep going around in the cycle of rebirth anymore. Yeah, that's very much like Lama Chöni. Okay, next sentence. Now the concept he wants to talk about is
'CHING
BA' and 'GROL BA'. I want to jump to the Sanskrit lesson, which is the next slide. I mainly did this for Christina because she likes it. We're going to discuss 'CHING BA' and 'GROL BA'. This chapter is called "Binding and Liberation" or "Handcuffs and Freedom" or something like that. We've been
discussing
who's being handcuffed? Who is handcuffed? Let's first look at the Sanskrit words used here, so that you can learn some Sanskrit and speak it when you become the Medicine Buddha. The first word: BANDHA. BANDHA is also used in yoga, right? Pao, what is BANDHA? Yes, lock,
we call it lock. Similar to
that, GRANTHI is worse. GRANTHI is like a knot in the energy channels, but BANDHA is deliberate... It's probably here. I don't understand, I can't do it
very well. It's just tightening
your stomach, that's BANDHA lock. The spelling of BANDHA is the same technically. It's all English pronunciation of BANDHA. In Tibetan it's '
CHING BA'. I learned 'CHING BA' from Tibetan newspapers. They kept mentioning 'CHING GROL DMAG MI', the People's Liberation Army of China. In Tibetan, the Chinese national army is called 'CHING GROL DMAG MI', the army that
liberates handcuffs, the People's Liberation Army of China. So 'CHING' refers to
handcuffs. 'CHING BA's root is √BANDH, meaning to tie up. Has Master Jigme
ever been to a bus station in India?
Everyone is on strike, and they will keep shouting: BANDH KARO We are on strike, we are on strike. BANDH means they have tied up all the buses, so they can't go anywhere.
Indo-European word is √BHENDH, which evolved into bind, band, and bundle.
Therefore, it is easy to
see that BANDHA means being tied to the cycle of
reincarnation.
What is the opposite? The next one is MUKTI or MOKSHA. SHA is a retroflex sound; you need to curl your tongue back. MOKSHA, in Tibetan, is GROL BA, like SGROL MA
, Tara (Tara). The root is √muc or √mokṣ, meaning liberation. I think the Indo-European word MUC means slippery,
like the viscous fluid mucus, which comes from it. I think it refers to sliding out of samsara,
but
I didn't include it here because it's a bit too much. In your...
I think it's all related to the Indo-European word √mittere.
You can also find it in Latin, meaning to send a message or mission. It means to liberate someone, understand? Now let's return to the text, and the slides should go back to SKYE 'JIG CHOS CAN 'DU BYED RNAMS, MI
'CHING GROL BAR MI 'GYUR TE
. Don't forget that 'DU BYED' here refers to mind and body. The spelling is slightly different. How do you remove the handcuffs from a SKYE 'JIG? How do you free a person from someone who is sometimes present and sometimes absent, every
single second? How do you remove the handcuffs from someone who is unchanging or someone who changes every thousandth of a second? The moment you put your hand on his handcuffs, he becomes a different person. How...who is there? Who has a permanent body and
mind to stay there so you can remove his handcuffs? Because if he is eternal, it means he is unchanging, and that's impossible. You can't remove the handcuffs from an eternally existing person because he can't change.
So he can't go from having handcuffs to not having handcuffs
because he can't change. You can't remove the handcuffs from an unchanging person because removing the handcuffs is equivalent to
changing him, understand? If he changes every millisecond, by the time your hand touches his handcuffs, they'll already belong to someone else. Do you understand? SNGA MA BZHIN DU SEMS CAN YANG, MI 'CHING
GROL BAR MI 'GYUR RO, SNGA MA BZHIN means that we follow the previous pattern. We have defined that you cannot remove the chains
from Patch's mind and body. Why? Because if they last for a period of time, it means they are immutable. But if they
don't last for a period of time, when you touch the handcuffs, they have become something else. If this applies to Patch's mind and body, then it also applies to Patch. This is the second
part of that verse.
He is performing the same RIM PA. What
is that? Similarly, these parallel arguments, after dealing with Patch's
mind and body, then come to dealing with Patch himself. You cannot remove the chains from Patch's mind and body because they can only be
changeable or unchanging, and
you cannot remove the chains from either. You also cannot remove the chains from Patch, that is, from the aluminum Rebecca who is constantly reincarnated, constantly
abandoning her mind and body and acquiring a new one, because it's just a change of form without substance. If he is changeable, you don't have time to remove his handcuffs, and if he is unchanging,
he cannot go from having handcuffs to not having handcuffs,
because then he is changeable, understand? So it's unreasonable that you can liberate someone. Something's not right. That's what Nagarjuna is saying. The whole chapter is saying that it's unreasonable for Patch to
enter the cycle of reincarnation, and it's also unreasonable for you to take Patch out of the cycle of reincarnation. Something's not right. There's a big problem here. Why does he talk about liberation and
handcuffs
? I
guess it's because we've put a lot of effort into this.
We're reading his book because we want to change our lives. That's the primary reason we read his book. Okay, let's continue. Oh, we've finished this chapter, yay! Let's summarize.
If Patch is the person from one life to the next, then he is unchanging because he is the
unchanging Patch who keeps acquiring new bodies and minds, discarding them, and
then acquiring new bodies and minds again. This implies that Patch can exist even without a body and mind, which is insane. And if there is no Patch, then who holds his body and mind? If
Patch is merely his body and soul, then who goes to the next life? If this body and mind die, Patch
disappears
because he is just his body and mind. No, Patch is the soul that holds his body and mind. So he is unchanging and
can only remain in the cycle of reincarnation forever, unable to escape. Something
's
wrong with
Patch.
Okay, let's move on to the next chapter, yay!